<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<Classes version="1.3.0">
    <!--The file contains following classes
BioMaterialCharacteristics
BioSequenceType
ExperimentDesignType
ProtocolType
ExperimentalFactorCategory
TechnologyType
-->
    <Class name="BioMaterialCharacteristics">
        <Description>Properties of the biomaterial before treated in any manner for the purposes of the experiment.</Description>
        <Class name="Age">
            <Description>The time period elapsed since an identifiable point in the life cycle of an organism. If a developmental stage is specified, the identifiable point would be the beginning of that stage. Otherwise the identifiable point must be specified such as planting (e.g. 3 days post planting).</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="BioMaterialPurity">
            <Description>A measure of homogeneity of a biomaterial. For example, an expression of the  percentage of a tumor biopsy that is tumor cells.</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Biometrics">
            <Description>Physical properties of the BioMaterial e. g. mass or height</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="BioSourceProvider">
            <Description>The resource (e.g. company, hospital, geographical location) used to obtain or purchase the biomaterial. </Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="BioSourceType">
            <Description>The form in which the BioMaterial was obtained/maintained e.g. frozen, fresh etc. Note can be used to describe BioSamples as well as BioSources.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="urine"/>
                <Instance name="blood"/>
                <Instance name="freeze_dried_sample"/>
                <Instance name="frozen_sample"/>
                <Instance name="feces"/>
                <Instance name="fresh_sample"/>
                <Instance name="agar_stab"/>
                <Instance name="paraffin_sample"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="CellLine">
            <Description>The identifier for the established culture of a metazoan cell if one was used as a biomaterial.

</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="CellType">
            <Description>CellType, the type of cell used in the experiment if non mixed, if mixed the TargetedCellType should be used, example of instances, epithelial, glial etc.</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="ChromosomalAberrationClassification">
            <Description>An irregularity in the number or structure of chromosomes, usually in the form of a gain (duplication), loss (deletion), exchange (translocation), or alteration in sequence (inversion) of genetic material. Excludes simple changes in sequence such as mutations, and is usually detectable by cytogenetic and microscopic techniques such as FISH.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="chromosomal_translocation"/>
                <Instance name="monosomy"/>
                <Instance name="oligosomy"/>
                <Instance name="trisomy"/>
                <Instance name="polysomy"/>
                <Instance name="chromosomal_insertion"/>
                <Instance name="genomic_region_amplification"/>
                <Instance name="chromosomal_inversion"/>
                <Instance name="chromosomal_deletion"/>
                <Instance name="chromosomal_duplication"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="ClinicalTreatment">
            <Description>The current clinical treatment(s) of the patient from which the biosource is derived.</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="DevelopmentalStage">
            <Description>The developmental stage of the organism's life cycle during which the biomaterial was extracted. 
</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="DiseaseStaging">
            <Description>The stage or progression of a disease in an organism. Includes pathological staging of cancers and other disease progression. </Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="DiseaseState">
            <Description>The name of the pathology diagnosed in the organism from which the biomaterial was derived. The disease state is normal if no disease has been diagnosed. 
</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="EnvironmentalHistory">
            <Description>A description of the conditions the organism has been exposed to that are not one of the variables under study. </Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="environmental_history_design"/>
            </Instances>
            <Class name="Bedding">
                <Description>Refers to the bedding material present in an animals housing.</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="ClinicalHistory">
                <Description>The BioMaterial's (i.e., the patient's) medical record as background information relevant to the experiment.</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="FamilyHistory">
                <Description>Relevant aspects of genetic preconditions or family member's clinical history.</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="Generation">
                <Description>The number of cell passages if the organism or organism part that is cultured is unicellular or a cell culture otherwise the number of generations.</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="GeographicLocation">
                <Description>A descriptor of the location from which a BioMaterial was obtained, e.g. country, region, grid reference.</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="GrowthCondition">
                <Description>A description of the conditions used to grow organisms or parts of the organism. This includes isolated environments such as cultures and open environments such as field studies.</Description>
                <Class name="Atmosphere">
                    <Description>The atmospheric conditions used to culture or grow an organism.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="BarrierFacility">
                    <Description>Rating of containment system for the protection of organisms from infectious agents.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Humidity">
                    <Description>The humidity that the biosource is exposed to.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Light">
                    <Description>The photoperiod and type (e.g., natural, restricted wavelength) of light exposure. </Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Media">
                    <Description>The physical state or matrix used to provide nutrients to the organism (e.g., liquid, agar, soil) .</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="semisolid"/>
                        <Instance name="liquid"/>
                        <Instance name="soil"/>
                        <Instance name="agar"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Nutrients">
                    <Description>The food provided to the organism (e.g., chow, fertilizer, DEMM 10%FBS, etc.).</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="PopulationDensity">
                    <Description>The concentration range of the organism.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Temperature">
                    <Description>The temperature that a biosource is exposed to.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Water">
                    <Description>Water consumed by or enveloping the organism that the biosource is derived from. </Description>
                </Class>
            </Class>
            <Class name="Host">
                <Description>Organisms or organism parts used as a designed part of the culture (e.g., red blood cells, stromal cells). </Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="PathogenTest">
                <Description>Tests and results for pathogens infecting organism from which the biosource is derived</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="SamplingTimePoint">
                <Description>A descriptor of the time point that a sample was taken. Not to be used 
    where the sample is part of a time course. SamplingTimePoint is not 
    related to age. An instance could be summer, a date, a time, or a range 
    value.</Description>
            </Class>
        </Class>
        <Class name="GeneticModification">
            <Description>The genetic modification introduced into the organism from which the biomaterial was derived. Examples of genetic modification include specification of a transgene or the gene knocked-out or details of transient transfection.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="transfection"/>
                <Instance name="gene_knock_in"/>
                <Instance name="induced_mutation"/>
                <Instance name="gene_knock_out"/>
                <Instance name="chromosomal_substitution"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Histology">
            <Description>Microscopic morphology of tissues.</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Individual">
            <Description>Identifier or name of the individual organism from which the biomaterial was derived. </Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="IndividualGeneticCharacteristics">
            <Description>The genotype of the individual organism from which the biomaterial was derived. Individual genetic characteristics include polymorphisms, disease alleles, and haplotypes.</Description>
            <Class name="Allele">
                <Description>One of two or more alternative forms of a gene or marker sequence and differing from other alleles at one or more mutational sites based on phenotype or sequence. Polymorphisms are included in this definition.</Description>
                <Instances>
                    <Instance name="wild_type"/>
                </Instances>
            </Class>
            <Class name="Genotype">
                <Description>The total sum of the genetic information of an organism that is known and relevant to the experiment being performed, including chromosomal, plasmid, viral or other genetic material which has been introduced into the organism
either prior to or during the experiment.</Description>
                <Instances>
                    <Instance name="wild_type"/>
                </Instances>
            </Class>
            <Class name="Haplotype">
                <Description>The genotype of a single chromosome (i.e., the haploid genotype) that is known and relevant to the experiment being performed. </Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="IndividualChromosomalAbnormality">
                <Description>An abnormality in the number or structure of chromosomes in the biomaterial from an individual organism, detected by karyotyping or other methods. E.g., a B-cell lymphoma from a patient has an abnormal karyotype 48,XY,t(1;2)(p22;p11),+3,+12.</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="Ploidy">
                <Description>The number of single sets of chromosomes in the cell or an organism e.g., haploid, diploid, triploid, etc.</Description>
                <Instances>
                    <Instance name="polyploid"/>
                    <Instance name="haploid"/>
                    <Instance name="diploid"/>
                    <Instance name="aneuploid"/>
                </Instances>
            </Class>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Observation">
            <Description>Observation will record the macroscopic examination of the biomaterial.</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Organism">
            <Description>The genus and species (and subspecies) of the organism from which the biomaterial is derived from. </Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="OrganismPart">
            <Description>The part of organism's anatomy or substance arising from an organism from which the biomaterial was derived, excludes cells. E.g. tissue, organ, system, sperm, blood or body location (arm).
</Description>
            <Class name="DiseaseLocation">
                <Description>Anatomical location(s) of disease.</Description>
            </Class>
        </Class>
        <Class name="OrganismStatus">
            <Description>The stage premortem or postmortem at which the sample was processed for extraction of biomaterials. </Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="postmortem"/>
                <Instance name="premortem"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Phenotype">
            <Description>The observable form taken by some character (or group of characters) in an individual or an organism, excluding pathology and disease.  The detectable outward manifestations of a specific genotype.</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Serotype">
            <Description>An antigenic property of a cell (e.g. bacteria, RBC) or virus identified by serological methods</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Sex">
            <Description>Term applied to any organism able to undergo sexual reproduction in order to differentiate the individuals or types involved. Sexual reproduction is defined as the ability to exchange genetic material with the potential of recombinant progeny.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="hermaphrodite"/>
                <Instance name="mating_type_h_minus"/>
                <Instance name="Hfr"/>
                <Instance name="mixed_sex"/>
                <Instance name="female"/>
                <Instance name="mating_type_alpha"/>
                <Instance name="male"/>
                <Instance name="mating_type_a"/>
                <Instance name="F_minus"/>
                <Instance name="F"/>
                <Instance name="mating_type_h_plus"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_sex"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="StrainOrLine">
            <Description>A strain or line is an animal or plant offspring that has a single ancestral breeding pair or parent as a result of brother x sister or parent x offspring matings. This class is extended to include F1 offspring and established breeding lines. For microbes, these are isolates derived from nature or in the laboratory.</Description>
            <Class name="Cultivar">
                <Description> a plant variety obtained in agriculture in horticulture</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="Ecotype">
                <Description>a biotype resulting from selection in a particular habitat, e.g. the A. thaliana Ecotype Ler
</Description>
            </Class>
        </Class>
        <Class name="TargetedCellType">
            <Description>The target cell type is the cell of primary interest. The biomaterial may be derived from a mixed population of cells although only one cell type is of interest. 
</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="Test">
            <Description>An assay performed on a biomaterial for the purposes of determining one or more biomaterial characteristics e.g. clinical chemistry.
</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="TestResult">
            <Description>TestResult is the recorded value of the test outcome.</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="TestType">
            <Description>Descriptor of the Test performed e.g. Leukocyte count</Description>
        </Class>
        <Class name="TumorGrading">
            <Description>A descriptor used in cancer biology to describe abnormalities of tumor cells. E.g. an instance from NCI Thesaurus. </Description>
        </Class>
    </Class>
    <Class name="BioSequenceType">
        <Description>Controlled terms for descriptors indicating the type of biosequence. Types may be physical (e.g. BAC, cDNA clone), or  computational (e.g. unigene cluster, consensus).</Description>
        <Class name="PhysicalBioSequenceType">
            <Description>A physical biosequence type represents biological sequence that can be physically placed (spotted or synthesized) on an array e.g. BAC, PAC.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="ds_oligo"/>
                <Instance name="clone_of_unknown_source"/>
                <Instance name="PCR_primer_forward"/>
                <Instance name="plasmid"/>
                <Instance name="PCR_amplicon"/>
                <Instance name="polypeptide"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_sequence"/>
                <Instance name="vector"/>
                <Instance name="ss_oligo"/>
                <Instance name="chromosome"/>
                <Instance name="mtDNA"/>
                <Instance name="ctDNA"/>
                <Instance name="PCR_primer_reverse"/>
                <Instance name="PCR_primer"/>
                <Instance name="YAC"/>
                <Instance name="antibody"/>
                <Instance name="cosmid"/>
                <Instance name="PAC"/>
                <Instance name="cDNA_clone"/>
                <Instance name="BAC"/>
            </Instances>
            <Class name="SequenceOntologyBioSequenceType">
                <Description>Descriptors of biosequence based on the Sequence Ontology (SO) project.</Description>
            </Class>
        </Class>
        <Class name="TheoreticalBioSequenceType">
            <Description>A theoretical biosequence type is an abstraction used for annotation design of elements, e.g. gene, intron.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="consensus_DNA"/>
                <Instance name="EST"/>
                <Instance name="ORF"/>
                <Instance name="consensus_mRNA"/>
                <Instance name="intergenic"/>
                <Instance name="gene"/>
                <Instance name="polypeptide"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_sequence"/>
                <Instance name="chromosome"/>
                <Instance name="exon"/>
                <Instance name="exemplar_mRNA"/>
                <Instance name="intron"/>
                <Instance name="operon"/>
                <Instance name="mRNA"/>
                <Instance name="transcript"/>
                <Instance name="predicted_gene"/>
                <Instance name="tRNA_gene"/>
                <Instance name="gene_fragment"/>
                <Instance name="promoter"/>
                <Instance name="rRNA_gene"/>
                <Instance name="snRNA_gene"/>
            </Instances>
            <Class name="SequenceOntologyBioSequenceType">
                <Description>Descriptors of biosequence based on the Sequence Ontology (SO) project.</Description>
            </Class>
        </Class>
    </Class>
    <Class name="ExperimentDesignType">
        <Description>The ExperimentDesignType is the high level description for studies such as "time series", "dose response", etc.  </Description>
        <Class name="BiologicalProperty">
            <Description>A biological property experiment design type is where an intrinsic characteristic of an organism(s) or biological system is examined.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="innate_behavior_design"/>
                <Instance name="strain_or_line_design"/>
                <Instance name="is_expressed_design"/>
                <Instance name="individual_genetic_characteristics_design"/>
                <Instance name="behavior_design"/>
                <Instance name="circadian_rhythm_design"/>
                <Instance name="physiological_process_design"/>
                <Instance name="sex_design"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_experiment_design_type"/>
                <Instance name="species_design"/>
                <Instance name="cell_type_comparison_design"/>
                <Instance name="cellular_process_design"/>
                <Instance name="cell_cycle_design"/>
                <Instance name="organism_status_design"/>
                <Instance name="development_or_differentiation_design"/>
                <Instance name="imprinting_design"/>
                <Instance name="organism_part_comparison_design"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="BioMolecularAnnotation">
            <Description>BioMolecularAnnotation experiment design types are those which are designed to investigate functions, processes, locations and identity at the molecular level e.g. binding site identification, genotyping.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="tiling_path_design"/>
                <Instance name="transcript_identification_design">
                    <Synonym name="gene expression"/>
                    <Synonym name="gene_expression"/>
                    <Synonym name="expression_profiling"/>
                    <Synonym name="transcription_profiling"/>
                    <Synonym name="expression profiling"/>
                    <Synonym name="transcription profiling"/>
                </Instance>
                <Instance name="RNA_stability_design"/>
                <Instance name="genotyping_design"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_experiment_design_type"/>
                <Instance name="secreted_protein_identification_design"/>
                <Instance name="operon_identification_design"/>
                <Instance name="comparative_genome_hybridization_design">
                    <Synonym name="CGH"/>
                    <Synonym name="array CGH"/>
                    <Synonym name="array_CGH"/>
                </Instance>
                <Instance name="co-expression_design"/>
                <Instance name="binding_site_identification_design">
                    <Synonym name="ChIP-chip"/>
                    <Synonym name="chromatin_immunoprecipitation"/>
                    <Synonym name="chromatin immunoprecipitation"/>
                </Instance>
                <Instance name="translational_bias_design"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="EpidemiologicalDesign">
            <Description>An epidemiological experiment design type is where the biosource history is studied e.g. environmental, clinical and family history.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="family_history_design"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_experiment_design_type"/>
                <Instance name="clinical_history_design"/>
                <Instance name="disease_state_design"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="MethodologicalDesign">
            <Description>A methodological experiment design type investigates differences caused by application of protocols, hardware, software and bioassay relationships, e.g. quality control, replicates, loop.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="in_vitro_design"/>
                <Instance name="in_vivo_design"/>
                <Instance name="self_vs_self_design"/>
                <Instance name="operator_variation_design"/>
                <Instance name="all_pairs"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_experiment_design_type"/>
                <Instance name="software_variation_design"/>
                <Instance name="reference_design"/>
                <Instance name="normalization_testing_design"/>
                <Instance name="hardware_variation_design"/>
                <Instance name="ex_vivo_design"/>
                <Instance name="dye_swap_design"/>
                <Instance name="replicate_design"/>
                <Instance name="time_series_design"/>
                <Instance name="array_platform_variation_design"/>
                <Instance name="loop_design"/>
                <Instance name="optimization_design"/>
                <Instance name="quality_control_testing_design"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="PerturbationalDesign">
            <Description>A perturbational design type is where the organism(s) are treated or manipulated or modified, for example a genetic modification, somatic modification </Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="cellular_modification_design">
                    <Synonym name="RNAi"/>
                </Instance>
                <Instance name="genetic_modification_design"/>
                <Instance name="dose_response_design"/>
                <Instance name="compound_treatment_design"/>
                <Instance name="stimulus_or_stress_design"/>
                <Instance name="growth_condition_design"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_experiment_design_type"/>
                <Instance name="injury_design"/>
                <Instance name="behavioral_design_type"/>
                <Instance name="non-targeted_transgenic_variation_design"/>
                <Instance name="pathogenicity_design"/>
                <Instance name="disease_state_design"/>
                <Instance name="stimulated_design_type"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="TechnologicalDesign">
            <Description>The purpose(s) for which the array is used within an experiment, e.g. to 
    assess the transcriptome, the genomic content, or to identify 
    transcription factor binding sites.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="cellular_modification_design">
                    <Synonym name="RNAi"/>
                </Instance>
                <Instance name="transcript_identification_design">
                    <Synonym name="gene expression"/>
                    <Synonym name="gene_expression"/>
                    <Synonym name="expression_profiling"/>
                    <Synonym name="transcription_profiling"/>
                    <Synonym name="expression profiling"/>
                    <Synonym name="transcription profiling"/>
                </Instance>
                <Instance name="comparative_genome_hybridization_design">
                    <Synonym name="CGH"/>
                    <Synonym name="array CGH"/>
                    <Synonym name="array_CGH"/>
                </Instance>
                <Instance name="binding_site_identification_design">
                    <Synonym name="ChIP-chip"/>
                    <Synonym name="chromatin_immunoprecipitation"/>
                    <Synonym name="chromatin immunoprecipitation"/>
                </Instance>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
    </Class>
    <Class name="ProtocolType">
        <Description>A controlled set of terms to provide a descriptor for the type of protocol.</Description>
        <Class name="DataTransformationProtocolType">
            <Description>The process by which derived BioAssays are created from measured BioAssays and/or derived BioAssays.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="loess_group_normalization"/>
                <Instance name="lowess_scaled_group_normalization"/>
                <Instance name="replicate_analysis"/>
                <Instance name="loess_global_normalization"/>
                <Instance name="dye_swap_merge"/>
                <Instance name="quantile_normalization_protocol_type"/>
                <Instance name="total_intensity_normalization_single"/>
                <Instance name="loess_scaled_group_normalization"/>
                <Instance name="across_bioassay_data_set_function"/>
                <Instance name="mean_log_normalization"/>
                <Instance name="within_bioassay_data_set_function"/>
                <Instance name="moving_average"/>
                <Instance name="total_intensity_normalization_paired"/>
                <Instance name="lowess_global_normalization"/>
                <Instance name="low_intensity_filter"/>
                <Instance name="flag_filter"/>
                <Instance name="linlog_transformation"/>
                <Instance name="lowess_group_normalization"/>
                <Instance name="median_log_normalization"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="ExperimentalProtocolType">
            <Description>All protocols which involve treatment of a biomaterial or an array during the course of a microarray experiment.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="change_biomaterial_characteristics"/>
                <Instance name="PCR_amplification"/>
                <Instance name="starvation"/>
                <Instance name="dissect"/>
                <Instance name="decontaminate"/>
                <Instance name="purify"/>
                <Instance name="preservation"/>
                <Instance name="store"/>
                <Instance name="unknown_protocol_type"/>
                <Instance name="labeling"/>
                <Instance name="reverse_transcription"/>
                <Instance name="element_design"/>
                <Instance name="inoculate">
                    <Synonym name="infect"/>
                </Instance>
                <Instance name="wash"/>
                <Instance name="sacrifice"/>
                <Instance name="nucleic_acid_extraction"/>
                <Instance name="histological_slide_preparation"/>
                <Instance name="infect"/>
                <Instance name="behavioral_stimulus"/>
                <Instance name="biological_fluid_collection"/>
                <Instance name="grow"/>
                <Instance name="irradiate"/>
                <Instance name="acclimatization"/>
                <Instance name="pool"/>
                <Instance name="compound_based_treatment"/>
                <Instance name="array_manufacturing"/>
                <Instance name="split"/>
                <Instance name="transfect"/>
                <Instance name="fractionate"/>
                <Instance name="hybridization"/>
                <Instance name="genetic_modification"/>
                <Instance name="feature_extraction"/>
                <Instance name="image_acquisition"/>
                <Instance name="incubate"/>
                <Instance name="specified_biomaterial_action"/>
                <Instance name="harvest"/>
                <Instance name="linear_amplification"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="HigherLevelAnalysisProtocolType">
            <Description>A protocol which yields a dataset(s) from which biological conclusions can be derived. E.g. clustering (not normalization or averaging).</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="condition_specificity"/>
                <Instance name="multiple_testing_correction"/>
                <Instance name="differential_expression"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
    </Class>
    <Class name="ExperimentalFactorCategory">
        <Description>A factor category describes factors which are examined in the experiment,  e.g. disease_state, where the factor values are ALL and AML.</Description>
        <Class name="BiologicalFactorCategory">
            <Description>Factors that relate to properties of the biomaterial, its treatment, or 
    its growth.</Description>
            <Class name="Action">
                <Description>Procedures used during treatment.</Description>
                <Class name="AtomicAction">
                    <Description>An atomic action  is a single step process on the biomaterial, e.g. mix by inversion, wait, add</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="set_temperature"/>
                        <Instance name="resuspend"/>
                        <Instance name="place"/>
                        <Instance name="mix_by_pipette"/>
                        <Instance name="change_light"/>
                        <Instance name="change_temperature"/>
                        <Instance name="mix_by_inversion"/>
                        <Instance name="remove"/>
                        <Instance name="add"/>
                        <Instance name="spin"/>
                        <Instance name="mix_by_vortex"/>
                        <Instance name="concentrate"/>
                        <Instance name="change_humidity"/>
                        <Instance name="mix_general"/>
                        <Instance name="dilute"/>
                        <Instance name="specified_biomaterial_action"/>
                        <Instance name="wait"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="ComplexAction">
                    <Description>Complex actions are composed of multiple steps (as opposed to AtomicAction) e.g. mRNA labeling, protein purification.</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="change_biomaterial_characteristics"/>
                        <Instance name="PCR_amplification"/>
                        <Instance name="starvation"/>
                        <Instance name="dissect"/>
                        <Instance name="decontaminate"/>
                        <Instance name="purify"/>
                        <Instance name="preservation"/>
                        <Instance name="store"/>
                        <Instance name="labeling"/>
                        <Instance name="reverse_transcription"/>
                        <Instance name="inoculate">
                            <Synonym name="infect"/>
                        </Instance>
                        <Instance name="wash"/>
                        <Instance name="sacrifice"/>
                        <Instance name="nucleic_acid_extraction"/>
                        <Instance name="histological_slide_preparation"/>
                        <Instance name="infect"/>
                        <Instance name="behavioral_stimulus"/>
                        <Instance name="biological_fluid_collection"/>
                        <Instance name="biopsy"/>
                        <Instance name="timepoint"/>
                        <Instance name="grow"/>
                        <Instance name="irradiate"/>
                        <Instance name="acclimatization"/>
                        <Instance name="pool"/>
                        <Instance name="compound_based_treatment"/>
                        <Instance name="split"/>
                        <Instance name="transfect"/>
                        <Instance name="fractionate"/>
                        <Instance name="hybridization"/>
                        <Instance name="genetic_modification"/>
                        <Instance name="incubate"/>
                        <Instance name="specified_biomaterial_action"/>
                        <Instance name="harvest"/>
                        <Instance name="linear_amplification"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
            </Class>
            <Class name="BioMaterialCharacteristicCategory">
                <Description>General descriptor of a BioMaterialCharacteristic category.  Such as strain or line where the name of the strain or line is encoded in the FactorValue.  
</Description>
                <Instances>
                    <Instance name="clinical_treatment"/>
                    <Instance name="age"/>
                    <Instance name="organism"/>
                    <Instance name="cell_type"/>
                    <Instance name="genetic_variation"/>
                    <Instance name="cell_line"/>
                    <Instance name="biomaterial_provider"/>
                    <Instance name="bedding"/>
                    <Instance name="individual"/>
                    <Instance name="sex"/>
                    <Instance name="individual_genetic_characteristic"/>
                    <Instance name="disease_state"/>
                    <Instance name="disease_staging"/>
                    <Instance name="clinical_information"/>
                    <Instance name="tumor_grading"/>
                    <Instance name="strain_or_line"/>
                    <Instance name="physical_characteristics"/>
                    <Instance name="sampling_time_point"/>
                    <Instance name="organism_status"/>
                    <Instance name="developmental_stage"/>
                    <Instance name="organism_part"/>
                </Instances>
            </Class>
            <Class name="BioMaterialCharacteristics">
                <Description>Properties of the biomaterial before treated in any manner for the purposes of the experiment.</Description>
                <Class name="Age">
                    <Description>The time period elapsed since an identifiable point in the life cycle of an organism. If a developmental stage is specified, the identifiable point would be the beginning of that stage. Otherwise the identifiable point must be specified such as planting (e.g. 3 days post planting).</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="BioMaterialPurity">
                    <Description>A measure of homogeneity of a biomaterial. For example, an expression of the  percentage of a tumor biopsy that is tumor cells.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Biometrics">
                    <Description>Physical properties of the BioMaterial e. g. mass or height</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="BioSourceProvider">
                    <Description>The resource (e.g. company, hospital, geographical location) used to obtain or purchase the biomaterial. </Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="BioSourceType">
                    <Description>The form in which the BioMaterial was obtained/maintained e.g. frozen, fresh etc. Note can be used to describe BioSamples as well as BioSources.</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="urine"/>
                        <Instance name="blood"/>
                        <Instance name="freeze_dried_sample"/>
                        <Instance name="frozen_sample"/>
                        <Instance name="feces"/>
                        <Instance name="fresh_sample"/>
                        <Instance name="agar_stab"/>
                        <Instance name="paraffin_sample"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="CellLine">
                    <Description>The identifier for the established culture of a metazoan cell if one was used as a biomaterial.

</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="CellType">
                    <Description>CellType, the type of cell used in the experiment if non mixed, if mixed the TargetedCellType should be used, example of instances, epithelial, glial etc.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="ChromosomalAberrationClassification">
                    <Description>An irregularity in the number or structure of chromosomes, usually in the form of a gain (duplication), loss (deletion), exchange (translocation), or alteration in sequence (inversion) of genetic material. Excludes simple changes in sequence such as mutations, and is usually detectable by cytogenetic and microscopic techniques such as FISH.</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="chromosomal_translocation"/>
                        <Instance name="monosomy"/>
                        <Instance name="oligosomy"/>
                        <Instance name="trisomy"/>
                        <Instance name="polysomy"/>
                        <Instance name="chromosomal_insertion"/>
                        <Instance name="genomic_region_amplification"/>
                        <Instance name="chromosomal_inversion"/>
                        <Instance name="chromosomal_deletion"/>
                        <Instance name="chromosomal_duplication"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="ClinicalTreatment">
                    <Description>The current clinical treatment(s) of the patient from which the biosource is derived.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="DevelopmentalStage">
                    <Description>The developmental stage of the organism's life cycle during which the biomaterial was extracted. 
</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="DiseaseStaging">
                    <Description>The stage or progression of a disease in an organism. Includes pathological staging of cancers and other disease progression. </Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="DiseaseState">
                    <Description>The name of the pathology diagnosed in the organism from which the biomaterial was derived. The disease state is normal if no disease has been diagnosed. 
</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="EnvironmentalHistory">
                    <Description>A description of the conditions the organism has been exposed to that are not one of the variables under study. </Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="environmental_history_design"/>
                    </Instances>
                    <Class name="Bedding">
                        <Description>Refers to the bedding material present in an animals housing.</Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="ClinicalHistory">
                        <Description>The BioMaterial's (i.e., the patient's) medical record as background information relevant to the experiment.</Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="FamilyHistory">
                        <Description>Relevant aspects of genetic preconditions or family member's clinical history.</Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="Generation">
                        <Description>The number of cell passages if the organism or organism part that is cultured is unicellular or a cell culture otherwise the number of generations.</Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="GeographicLocation">
                        <Description>A descriptor of the location from which a BioMaterial was obtained, e.g. country, region, grid reference.</Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="GrowthCondition">
                        <Description>A description of the conditions used to grow organisms or parts of the organism. This includes isolated environments such as cultures and open environments such as field studies.</Description>
                        <Class name="Atmosphere">
                            <Description>The atmospheric conditions used to culture or grow an organism.</Description>
                        </Class>
                        <Class name="BarrierFacility">
                            <Description>Rating of containment system for the protection of organisms from infectious agents.</Description>
                        </Class>
                        <Class name="Humidity">
                            <Description>The humidity that the biosource is exposed to.</Description>
                        </Class>
                        <Class name="Light">
                            <Description>The photoperiod and type (e.g., natural, restricted wavelength) of light exposure. </Description>
                        </Class>
                        <Class name="Media">
                            <Description>The physical state or matrix used to provide nutrients to the organism (e.g., liquid, agar, soil) .</Description>
                            <Instances>
                                <Instance name="semisolid"/>
                                <Instance name="liquid"/>
                                <Instance name="soil"/>
                                <Instance name="agar"/>
                            </Instances>
                        </Class>
                        <Class name="Nutrients">
                            <Description>The food provided to the organism (e.g., chow, fertilizer, DEMM 10%FBS, etc.).</Description>
                        </Class>
                        <Class name="PopulationDensity">
                            <Description>The concentration range of the organism.</Description>
                        </Class>
                        <Class name="Temperature">
                            <Description>The temperature that a biosource is exposed to.</Description>
                        </Class>
                        <Class name="Water">
                            <Description>Water consumed by or enveloping the organism that the biosource is derived from. </Description>
                        </Class>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="Host">
                        <Description>Organisms or organism parts used as a designed part of the culture (e.g., red blood cells, stromal cells). </Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="PathogenTest">
                        <Description>Tests and results for pathogens infecting organism from which the biosource is derived</Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="SamplingTimePoint">
                        <Description>A descriptor of the time point that a sample was taken. Not to be used 
    where the sample is part of a time course. SamplingTimePoint is not 
    related to age. An instance could be summer, a date, a time, or a range 
    value.</Description>
                    </Class>
                </Class>
                <Class name="GeneticModification">
                    <Description>The genetic modification introduced into the organism from which the biomaterial was derived. Examples of genetic modification include specification of a transgene or the gene knocked-out or details of transient transfection.</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="transfection"/>
                        <Instance name="gene_knock_in"/>
                        <Instance name="induced_mutation"/>
                        <Instance name="gene_knock_out"/>
                        <Instance name="chromosomal_substitution"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Histology">
                    <Description>Microscopic morphology of tissues.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Individual">
                    <Description>Identifier or name of the individual organism from which the biomaterial was derived. </Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="IndividualGeneticCharacteristics">
                    <Description>The genotype of the individual organism from which the biomaterial was derived. Individual genetic characteristics include polymorphisms, disease alleles, and haplotypes.</Description>
                    <Class name="Allele">
                        <Description>One of two or more alternative forms of a gene or marker sequence and differing from other alleles at one or more mutational sites based on phenotype or sequence. Polymorphisms are included in this definition.</Description>
                        <Instances>
                            <Instance name="wild_type"/>
                        </Instances>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="Genotype">
                        <Description>The total sum of the genetic information of an organism that is known and relevant to the experiment being performed, including chromosomal, plasmid, viral or other genetic material which has been introduced into the organism
either prior to or during the experiment.</Description>
                        <Instances>
                            <Instance name="wild_type"/>
                        </Instances>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="Haplotype">
                        <Description>The genotype of a single chromosome (i.e., the haploid genotype) that is known and relevant to the experiment being performed. </Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="IndividualChromosomalAbnormality">
                        <Description>An abnormality in the number or structure of chromosomes in the biomaterial from an individual organism, detected by karyotyping or other methods. E.g., a B-cell lymphoma from a patient has an abnormal karyotype 48,XY,t(1;2)(p22;p11),+3,+12.</Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="Ploidy">
                        <Description>The number of single sets of chromosomes in the cell or an organism e.g., haploid, diploid, triploid, etc.</Description>
                        <Instances>
                            <Instance name="polyploid"/>
                            <Instance name="haploid"/>
                            <Instance name="diploid"/>
                            <Instance name="aneuploid"/>
                        </Instances>
                    </Class>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Observation">
                    <Description>Observation will record the macroscopic examination of the biomaterial.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Organism">
                    <Description>The genus and species (and subspecies) of the organism from which the biomaterial is derived from. </Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="OrganismPart">
                    <Description>The part of organism's anatomy or substance arising from an organism from which the biomaterial was derived, excludes cells. E.g. tissue, organ, system, sperm, blood or body location (arm).
</Description>
                    <Class name="DiseaseLocation">
                        <Description>Anatomical location(s) of disease.</Description>
                    </Class>
                </Class>
                <Class name="OrganismStatus">
                    <Description>The stage premortem or postmortem at which the sample was processed for extraction of biomaterials. </Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="postmortem"/>
                        <Instance name="premortem"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Phenotype">
                    <Description>The observable form taken by some character (or group of characters) in an individual or an organism, excluding pathology and disease.  The detectable outward manifestations of a specific genotype.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Serotype">
                    <Description>An antigenic property of a cell (e.g. bacteria, RBC) or virus identified by serological methods</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Sex">
                    <Description>Term applied to any organism able to undergo sexual reproduction in order to differentiate the individuals or types involved. Sexual reproduction is defined as the ability to exchange genetic material with the potential of recombinant progeny.</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="hermaphrodite"/>
                        <Instance name="mating_type_h_minus"/>
                        <Instance name="Hfr"/>
                        <Instance name="mixed_sex"/>
                        <Instance name="female"/>
                        <Instance name="mating_type_alpha"/>
                        <Instance name="male"/>
                        <Instance name="mating_type_a"/>
                        <Instance name="F_minus"/>
                        <Instance name="F"/>
                        <Instance name="mating_type_h_plus"/>
                        <Instance name="unknown_sex"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="StrainOrLine">
                    <Description>A strain or line is an animal or plant offspring that has a single ancestral breeding pair or parent as a result of brother x sister or parent x offspring matings. This class is extended to include F1 offspring and established breeding lines. For microbes, these are isolates derived from nature or in the laboratory.</Description>
                    <Class name="Cultivar">
                        <Description> a plant variety obtained in agriculture in horticulture</Description>
                    </Class>
                    <Class name="Ecotype">
                        <Description>a biotype resulting from selection in a particular habitat, e.g. the A. thaliana Ecotype Ler
</Description>
                    </Class>
                </Class>
                <Class name="TargetedCellType">
                    <Description>The target cell type is the cell of primary interest. The biomaterial may be derived from a mixed population of cells although only one cell type is of interest. 
</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="Test">
                    <Description>An assay performed on a biomaterial for the purposes of determining one or more biomaterial characteristics e.g. clinical chemistry.
</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="TestResult">
                    <Description>TestResult is the recorded value of the test outcome.</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="TestType">
                    <Description>Descriptor of the Test performed e.g. Leukocyte count</Description>
                </Class>
                <Class name="TumorGrading">
                    <Description>A descriptor used in cancer biology to describe abnormalities of tumor cells. E.g. an instance from NCI Thesaurus. </Description>
                </Class>
            </Class>
            <Class name="Compound">
                <Description>A drug, solvent, chemical, etc., with a property that can be measured such as concentration.</Description>
                <Class name="LabelCompound">
                    <Description>Compounds that are used for labeling extracts.</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="alexa_633"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_532"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_430"/>
                        <Instance name="_33P"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_488"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_594"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_546"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_350"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_660"/>
                        <Instance name="Cy5"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_568"/>
                        <Instance name="Cy3"/>
                        <Instance name="biotin"/>
                        <Instance name="alexa_680"/>
                        <Instance name="_32P"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
            </Class>
        </Class>
        <Class name="EnvironmentalFactorCategory">
            <Description>Factors that relate to properties of the environmental history of the biomaterial, its treatment, or its growth.</Description>
            <Instances>
                <Instance name="water"/>
                <Instance name="relative_humidity"/>
                <Instance name="atmosphere"/>
                <Instance name="barrier_facility"/>
                <Instance name="light_intensity"/>
                <Instance name="media"/>
                <Instance name="light_duration"/>
                <Instance name="population_density"/>
                <Instance name="temperature"/>
                <Instance name="nutrients"/>
            </Instances>
        </Class>
        <Class name="MethodologicalFactorCategory">
            <Description>The effects on results of changing protocols, hardware, software, or people performing the experiments are studied Examples are comparison of data across different labeling protocols, scanners, image quantification software, or laboratories. </Description>
            <Class name="HardwareVariation">
                <Description>The effects of different hardware, types of hardware, or models of hardware on experimental results are studied.</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="OperatorVariation">
                <Description>The effects of different investigators, laboratories, or organizations on experimental results are studied.</Description>
            </Class>
            <Class name="ProtocolType">
                <Description>A controlled set of terms to provide a descriptor for the type of protocol.</Description>
                <Class name="DataTransformationProtocolType">
                    <Description>The process by which derived BioAssays are created from measured BioAssays and/or derived BioAssays.</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="loess_group_normalization"/>
                        <Instance name="lowess_scaled_group_normalization"/>
                        <Instance name="replicate_analysis"/>
                        <Instance name="loess_global_normalization"/>
                        <Instance name="dye_swap_merge"/>
                        <Instance name="quantile_normalization_protocol_type"/>
                        <Instance name="total_intensity_normalization_single"/>
                        <Instance name="loess_scaled_group_normalization"/>
                        <Instance name="across_bioassay_data_set_function"/>
                        <Instance name="mean_log_normalization"/>
                        <Instance name="within_bioassay_data_set_function"/>
                        <Instance name="moving_average"/>
                        <Instance name="total_intensity_normalization_paired"/>
                        <Instance name="lowess_global_normalization"/>
                        <Instance name="low_intensity_filter"/>
                        <Instance name="flag_filter"/>
                        <Instance name="linlog_transformation"/>
                        <Instance name="lowess_group_normalization"/>
                        <Instance name="median_log_normalization"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="ExperimentalProtocolType">
                    <Description>All protocols which involve treatment of a biomaterial or an array during the course of a microarray experiment.</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="change_biomaterial_characteristics"/>
                        <Instance name="PCR_amplification"/>
                        <Instance name="starvation"/>
                        <Instance name="dissect"/>
                        <Instance name="decontaminate"/>
                        <Instance name="purify"/>
                        <Instance name="preservation"/>
                        <Instance name="store"/>
                        <Instance name="unknown_protocol_type"/>
                        <Instance name="labeling"/>
                        <Instance name="reverse_transcription"/>
                        <Instance name="element_design"/>
                        <Instance name="inoculate">
                            <Synonym name="infect"/>
                        </Instance>
                        <Instance name="wash"/>
                        <Instance name="sacrifice"/>
                        <Instance name="nucleic_acid_extraction"/>
                        <Instance name="histological_slide_preparation"/>
                        <Instance name="infect"/>
                        <Instance name="behavioral_stimulus"/>
                        <Instance name="biological_fluid_collection"/>
                        <Instance name="grow"/>
                        <Instance name="irradiate"/>
                        <Instance name="acclimatization"/>
                        <Instance name="pool"/>
                        <Instance name="compound_based_treatment"/>
                        <Instance name="array_manufacturing"/>
                        <Instance name="split"/>
                        <Instance name="transfect"/>
                        <Instance name="fractionate"/>
                        <Instance name="hybridization"/>
                        <Instance name="genetic_modification"/>
                        <Instance name="feature_extraction"/>
                        <Instance name="image_acquisition"/>
                        <Instance name="incubate"/>
                        <Instance name="specified_biomaterial_action"/>
                        <Instance name="harvest"/>
                        <Instance name="linear_amplification"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
                <Class name="HigherLevelAnalysisProtocolType">
                    <Description>A protocol which yields a dataset(s) from which biological conclusions can be derived. E.g. clustering (not normalization or averaging).</Description>
                    <Instances>
                        <Instance name="condition_specificity"/>
                        <Instance name="multiple_testing_correction"/>
                        <Instance name="differential_expression"/>
                    </Instances>
                </Class>
            </Class>
            <Class name="SoftwareVariation">
                <Description>The effects of different software, software packages, or software versions on experimental results are studied.</Description>
            </Class>
        </Class>
    </Class>
    <Class name="TechnologyType">
        <Description>The technology type or platform of the reporters on the array.</Description>
        <Instances>
            <Instance name="spotted_antibody_features"/>
            <Instance name="spotted_ds_DNA_features"/>
            <Instance name="in_situ_oligo_features"/>
            <Instance name="spotted_ss_oligo_features"/>
            <Instance name="spotted_colony_features"/>
            <Instance name="spotted_ss_PCR_amplicon_features"/>
            <Instance name="spotted_protein_features"/>
        </Instances>
    </Class>
</Classes>